<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="Visual_Web_Tools" xreflabel="Visual_Web_Tools">
 <?dbhtml filename="Visual_Web_Tools.html"?>
 <chapterinfo>
  <keywordset>
   <keyword>JBoss Developer Studio</keyword>
   <keyword>JBDS</keyword>
   <keyword>Java</keyword>
   <keyword>Web Tools</keyword>
  </keywordset>
 </chapterinfo>

 <title>Visual Web Tools</title>

 <para>This guide covers the usage of Visual Web Tools in <property>JBoss Developer
  Studio</property> and <property>JBoss Tools</property>. The difference between these products is
  that JBoss Tools are just a set of Eclipse plugins where JBoss Developer Studio adds the following functionality:</para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>an installer</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>Eclipse and Web Tools preconfigured</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>JBoss EAP with JBoss AS and Seam preconfigured</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>3rd party plugins bundled and configured</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>access to RHEL and Red Hat Network</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>access to the JBoss/Red Hat supported software</para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>

 <para>For additional information, please visit the JBoss Developer Studio home page at: <ulink
   url="http://www.jboss.com/products/devstudio">http://www.jboss.com/products/devstudio</ulink>.</para>

 <para>In JBoss Tools there is an extensive collection of specialized wizards, editors and views
  that can be used in various scenarios while developing Web applications. The following chapters
  walk through these features.</para>

 <section id="key_features">
  <title>Key Features of Visual Web Tools</title>
  <para>Here is the table of the main features of Visual Web Tools:</para>

  <table>

   <title>Key Functionality for Visual Web Tools</title>
   <tgroup cols="3">

    <colspec colnum="1" align="left" colwidth="2*"/>
    <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="4*"/>
    <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="2*" align="left" />

    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>Feature</entry>
      <entry>Benefit</entry>
      <entry>Chapter</entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>Visual Page Editor</entry>
      <entry>Powerful and customizable visual page editor. Possibility to develop an application
       using any web technology: jsf, seam, struts, jsp, html and others. Developing using four
       tabs: visual/source, visual, source and preview. Fast and easy switching between these tabs.
       Split screen design of visual and source views. Full and instant synchronization between
       source and visual views. Integration with properties and outline views. Graphical toolbar to
       add inline styling to any tag.</entry>
      <entry>
       <link linkend="visual_page">visual page editor</link>
      </entry>
     </row>


     <row>
      <entry>Multiple Editors</entry>
      <entry>An extensive collection of specialized editors for different file types: properties, TLD, web.xml, tiles, and so on: Graphical Properties Editor,
       Graphical TLD Editor, Graphical Web Application File (web.xml) Editor, CSS Editor, JavaScript Editor, XSD Editor, Support for XML Schema.</entry>
      <entry>
       <link linkend="more_editors">more editors</link>
      </entry>
     </row>



     <row>
      <entry>JBoss Tools Palette</entry>
      <entry>Organizing various tags by groups, inserting tags into a jsp or xhtml page with one
       click, adding custom or 3rd party tag libraries into the palette, easy controlling the number
       of tag groups shown on the palette.</entry>
      <entry>
       <link linkend="palette">jboss tools palette</link>
      </entry>
     </row>

     <row>
      <entry>Web Projects View</entry>
      <entry>Visualizing and displaying projects by function. Easy selecting of different kinds of
       items and dropping them into jsp pages. Using context menus to develop the application. Using
       icon shortcuts to create and import JSF and Struts projects. Expanding and inspecting tag
       library files. Selecting custom and third-party tag libraries to drag and drop onto the JBoss
       Tools Palette.</entry>
      <entry>
       <link linkend="web_projects">web projects view</link>
      </entry>
     </row>

     <row>
      <entry>OpenOn</entry>
      <entry>Easy navigation between views and other parts of your projects.</entry>
      <entry>
       <link linkend="OpenOnSelection4Hyperlinknavigation">openOn</link>
      </entry>
     </row>

     <row>
      <entry>Content Assist</entry>
      <entry>Code completion proposals while working with html, java, JavaScript , xml, jsp, xhtml, xhtml, seam project
       and jsf configuration files. Content assist based on project data (dynamic code assist); with
       graphical editor. Code completion for values from property files, beans attributes and
       methods, navigation rule outcomes and jsf variables.</entry>
      <entry>
       <link linkend="CodeAssistAndDynamicCodeAssist42BasedOnProjectData">content assist</link>
      </entry>
     </row>

     <row>
      <entry>Drag-and-Drop</entry>
      <entry>Possibility of inserting any tag onto the page you are editing by just drag-and-droping
       it from the palette to this page. Adding any properties, managed bean attributes, navigation
       rules, tag library file declarations, jsp files from web projects view by clicking them and
       dragging to source code.</entry>
      <entry>
       <link linkend="visual_page">visual page editor</link>
       <link linkend="DragAndDrop">drag-and-drop</link>
      </entry>
     </row>

     <row>
      <entry>RichFaces Support</entry>
      <entry>Tight integration between JBDS and <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/jbossrichfaces">RichFaces</ulink> frameworks. Easy managing RichFaces
       components in any web application. Support for RichFaces and Ajax4jsf libraries in JBoss
       Tools Palette. Rendering RichFaces components in Visual Page Editor.</entry>
      <entry>
      	<link linkend="richfaces_support">RichFaces support</link>
      </entry>
     </row>
   
     <row>
      <entry>Flexible Configuration</entry>
      <entry>Various features of JBoss Developer Studio can be easily configured via the Preferences screen.</entry>
      <entry>
       <link linkend="preferences">preferences</link>
      </entry>
     </row>
    
    
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </table>
 </section>

<section>
 <title>Other relevant resources on the topic</title>
 <para>All JBoss Developer Studio/JBoss Tools release documentation you can find at<ulink url="http://docs.jboss.org/tools/">http://docs.jboss.org/tools</ulink> in the corresponding release directory.</para>
 <para>The latest documentation builds are available at <ulink url="http://download.jboss.org/jbosstools/nightly-docs/">http://download.jboss.org/jbosstools/nightly-docs</ulink>.</para>
</section>

</chapter>
