<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="generate_entities" xreflabel="generate_entities"> 
    <?dbhtml filename="generate_entities.html"?>
    <chapterinfo>
        <keywordset>
            <keyword>JBoss Tools</keyword>
            <keyword>Seam</keyword>
            <keyword>JBDS</keyword>
            </keywordset>
    </chapterinfo>
    
    <title>Seam Generate Entities</title>
    
    <para>The main purpose of this chapter is to tell you about Seam Generate Entities.</para>
    <para>Generate Entities is available directly from Eclipse using Hibernate Tools plugin for the standard seam-gen generation.</para>
    <para>The wizard generates a set of CRUD Seam components and web pages based on existing tables in a database or on existing entities in your application.</para>
    
    
    <figure>
        <title>Generate Seam Entities Wizard</title>
        <mediaobject> 
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/generate_entities/generate_entities1.png"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    
	<para>By default, the generation mode is set to <emphasis><property>Reverse engineer from database</property>.</emphasis> 
		The reverse engineering from a database could be described in four steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>The wizard gets in database, extracts the tables and 
            their connections</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>On basis of this metainfomation the Entity classes are generated into 
        	<literal>org.domain.project.entity</literal> package</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>For the entities from step 2 the classes <property>EntityList</property> and <property>EntityHome</property> are generated
        	into <literal>org.domain.project.session</literal> package</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>The xhtml pages are generated.</para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>
	
		<note>
			<title>Note:</title>
			<para>The entities are generated from a database based on the console configuration that is created automatically during a Seam project creation. 
				(Read more about console configuration). The created console configuration is based on the 
				connection profile set on the <link linkend="seamFacet">Seam Facets wizard page</link> while creating a project. 
				Configured connection profile settings are hold in the generated <literal>hibernate-console.properties</literal>. To change the connection
				profile, double-click the console configuration. It could be found in the <property>Hibernate Configurations</property> view 
				(<emphasis><property>Window &gt; Show view &gt; Other &gt; Hibernate &gt; Hibernate Configurations</property></emphasis>
				or just switch to the <property>Hibernate</property> perspective).</para>
		</note>
    <para>
    	Checking the <emphasis><property>Use existing entities</property></emphasis> mode the wizard executes only 3 and 4 steps. It generates missing classes and
        xhtml pages. 
    </para>
    
    <para>Read the <link linkend="crud_database_application">Generate a CRUD Database Application</link> chapter in order to see how the <property>Generate Seam Entities</property> wizard can be used.</para>
  </chapter>