<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="business_application" xreflabel="business_application">
 <?dbhtml filename="business_application.html"?>
  <chapterinfo>
        <keywordset>
            <keyword>Business process</keyword>
            <keyword>Seam</keyword>
            <keyword>JBoss Rules</keyword>
            <keyword>CRUD-application</keyword>
            </keywordset>
    </chapterinfo>
    
    <title>Business process and rules application</title>
    <para>Rules and business processes are important components in many enterprise applications. 
    They help business analysts to get involved in the design and implementation of the software
     project. Rules and business processes are also essential to complex internal states of large,
      multi-user systems. The JBoss Rules engine (formerly known as Drools) and jBPM business 
      process engine are two production-ready open source products supported by Red Hat. It is 
      very easy to incorporate rules and business processes into a Seam web application using the 
      JBoss Developer Studio. In this section, we further re-factor the CRUD application we
       already have and add support for an &quot;order management&quot; process.User scenario is to 
       simulate the following process and rules:</para>
       <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>The site administrator logs in and sees a list of outstanding orders</listitem>
       <listitem>She goes through the inventory (by hand or using another computer system) and 
       determines the availability of the products in each order. She enters that information to
        each order.</listitem>
        <listitem>She starts a process for each order, which determines whether to ship the order 
        or refund the order based on a business rule applied to the availability status. For 
        instance, an &quot;in stock&quot; status triggers a &quot;ship&quot; action while the &quot;back order&quot; status 
        triggers a &quot;refund&quot; action.</listitem>
        <listitem>When the business process reaches the &quot;ship&quot; or &quot;refund&quot; state, it will take 
        appropriate actions (e.g., to submit shipping orders to Fedex or to contact the credit
         card company for refund). In this simple case, we will just print out a message on the 
         console to prove that we can execute any code in those stages.</listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
         <para>While this process sounds simple, it is the basis for very complex business
          processes. In this section of the tutorial, we will show you how this is done via the 
          following steps:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>Add a rule definition to the application</listitem>
          <listitem>Add a business process that uses that rule to the application</listitem>
          <listitem>Start the business process from a web action</listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
<section id="ImportConfigurationFilesAndJavaCode">
<?dbhtml filename="ImportConfigurationFilesAndJavaCode.html"?>
<title>Import configuration files and Java code</title>
<para>Before we start, we need to import some configuration and Java files for the demo project. 
Those files are very simple and we will review them as we go along with the tutorial. We import 
them here to reduce potential typos and other errors in the tutorial.</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>Choose the <emphasis>File > Import ...</emphasis> menu and then select <emphasis>General > Existing</emphasis> project into workspace and 
click on the Next button.</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<figure>
<title>Importing Project</title>
<mediaobject> 
        <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="images/business_application/business_application_1.png"/>
        </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<orderedlist continuation="continues">
<listitem>To make this demo a little more manageable we have already created some demo code 
that is available in the rules-bpm directory of your tutorial distribution code. It is
 located in the root directory of the distribution.  Select the rules-bpm directory and check 
 the &quot;Copy projects into the workspace&quot; directory check box.</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>You will have a different directory on your machine than the screen shot shown below.</para>
<figure>
<title>Selecting Directory To Import</title>
<mediaobject> 
        <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="images/business_application/business_application_2.png"/>
        </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<orderedlist continuation="continues">
<listitem>After this step you will see a new project called &quot;rules-bpm&quot;. If you expand that 
directory, you will see numerous files as shown below. We will look at these files in this
 section of the demo. We will first start by copying these files into our EclipseCon project.</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<figure>
<title>Project Structure</title>
<mediaobject> 
        <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="images/business_application/business_application_3.png"/>
        </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<orderedlist continuation="continues">
<listitem>Right click on the rules-bpm/build.xml file, and select <emphasis>Run AS ... > Ant</emphasis> Build.</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<figure>
<title>AntBuild</title>
<mediaobject> 
        <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="images/business_application/business_application_4.png"/>
        </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<orderedlist continuation="continues">
<listitem>Right click on the EclipseCon project and select Refresh from the menu to pick up
 the changes made to the demo application. The rules-bpm/build.xml script copies a bunch of files
  into your existing EclipseCon project. We will look at them soon.</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
<section id="CreateARuledefinition">
<?dbhtml filename="CreateARuledefinition.html"?>
<title>Create a rule definition</title>
<para>In this section, we create a business rule that can be used in junction with the business
 process. When the rule is executed, it checks the status of the currently selected order. If the
  order status is &quot;in stock&quot;, meaning that a person has check off line and verified the 
  availability of the product ordered, the system changes the order status to &quot;ship&quot;, meaning
   that someone will now ship the product as the next step in the process. If the order status 
   is &quot;back order&quot;, the rule changes the order status to &quot;refund&quot; automatically to trigger the
    business process of refunding.</para>
    <orderedlist>
    <listitem>Select the<emphasis> EclipseCon/resources </emphasis>directory. That is where we are going to put the
     rules definition file.</listitem>
     <listitem>Select the following menu actions: <emphasis>File > New > Other ... > JBoss Rules > New
      Rules Resource</emphasis> to bring up the JBoss Rules wizard.</listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <figure>
<title>New Rules File</title>
<mediaobject> 
        <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="images/business_application/business_application_5.png"/>
        </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<orderedlist continuation="continues">
<listitem>Fill out the above window with the following values.</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<table>
         <title>Rule Table</title>
         <tgroup cols="2">
            <thead>
               <row>
                  <entry>Field Name</entry>
                  <entry>Field Value</entry>
               </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
               <row>
                  <entry>File Name</entry>
                  <entry>process-order.drl</entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>Type of Rule Resource</entry>
                  <entry>New DRL (rule package)</entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>Rule Package Name</entry>
                  <entry>process.order</entry>
               </row>
            </tbody>
         </tgroup>
      </table>
      <orderedlist continuation="continues">
<listitem>Replace the content of the process-order.drl file with the follow rule.</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[package process.order
		import com.mydomain.EclipseCon.Orders;

rule "Ship order rule"	
	when
	    order : Orders(status == "in stock")
	then 
		order.setStatus("ship");
end

rule "Refund order rule"	
	when
	    order : Orders(status == "back order")
	then 
		order.setStatus("refund");		
end
]]></programlisting>
<para>Notice that the IDE automatically highlights the syntax and provides auto-completion help.
 You may wonder how Seam knows to load the process-order.drl file for the application.</para>
 <para>If you look in the <emphasis><property>resources/WEB-INF/components.xml</property></emphasis> file we copied from the imported 
 rules-bpm project. It has an element pointing to the process-order.drl file.</para>
 <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<drools:rule-base name="securityRules">
       <drools:rule-files>
           <value>/security.drl</value>           
       </drools:rule-files>
   </drools:rule-base>
]]></programlisting>
</section>
<section id="CreateABusinessProcessDefinition">
<?dbhtml filename="CreateABusinessProcessDefinition.html"?>
<title>Create a business process definition</title>
<para>Next, let&apos;s create a business process that manages the order process. The business process
 essentially specifies a sequence of actions that has to happen before an order is shipped or 
 refunded. Since the business analyst typically designs this process, it is very high level and 
 can be drawn up in a GUI designer.</para>
 <orderedlist>
 <listitem>Select the<emphasis> EclipseCon/resources </emphasis>folder and select menu actions <emphasis>File > New > File</emphasis>.
  Add a new file called process-order.jpdl.xml as shown below:</listitem>
 </orderedlist>
 <figure>
<title>Creating New File Resource</title>
<mediaobject> 
        <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="images/business_application/business_application_6.png"/>
        </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<orderedlist continuation="continues">
<listitem>Add the following content to the process-order.jpdl.xml file. It is an empty jBPM 
process definition, and allows us to use the jBPM visual designer to further edit it.</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<process-definition
  xmlns=""  name="process-order">
</process-definition>
]]></programlisting>
<orderedlist continuation="continues">
<listitem>Right click on the process-order.jpdl.xml file and select <emphasis>Open with ... > jBPM 
Graphical Process Designer</emphasis>.</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<figure>
<title>Opening Graphical Process Designer</title>
<mediaobject> 
        <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="images/business_application/business_application_7.png"/>
        </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<orderedlist continuation="continues">
<listitem>In the designer, drag and drop nodes and transition lines until you have a process
 shown in the following image.  This is a high level process and aimed at business level non 
 technical users.</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>To draw a node, click on the type of the node in the palette. You should be able to see 
that based on the icon on the node as shown below. Draw a rectangle on the canvas and the
 appropriate node will be rendered.</para>
 <para>To draw a transition click on the transition icon in the palette, choose the source node
  and then the destination node. This will draw a transition from the source to the destination.</para>
  <para>To change the name on the node or transition, select the object and change the name in 
  the properties view or simply double click on the node or the transition line to change it.</para>
  <figure>
<title>Diagram View</title>
<mediaobject> 
        <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="images/business_application/business_application_8.png"/>
        </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<orderedlist continuation="continues">
<listitem>Save this file. You can click on the Source tab to view the generated XML file for
 the process.</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
<section id="AssociateProcessNodesWithJavaCode">
<?dbhtml filename="AssociateProcessNodesWithJavaCode.html"?>
<title>Associate process nodes with Java code</title>
<para>With the business process in the designer, we can now associate each node with Java code.
 The Java code is executed when the node is reached in the process, and the Java code determines
  the outcome of each node – hence the next node in the process.</para>
   <para>Let&apos;s go through the exercise for the &quot;Check Inventory&quot; node first.</para>
   <orderedlist>
   <listitem>Right click on the &quot;Check Inventory&quot; node in the designer and select <emphasis>Add 
   Actions > Node Enter </emphasis>from the menu as shown below.</listitem>
   </orderedlist>
   <figure>
<title>Node Entering</title>
<mediaobject> 
        <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="images/business_application/business_application_9.png"/>
        </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<orderedlist continuation="continues">
<listitem>In the Outline view tab, open the tree view of process-order > Check Inventory > 
node enter, and you will see action1. The Outline view may be hidden or on the left side of the
 IDE.</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<figure>
<title>Outline View</title>
<mediaobject> 
        <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="images/business_application/business_application_10.png"/>
        </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<orderedlist continuation="continues">
<listitem>Double click on action1 to bring up the wizard. Select Handler on the left and enter
 com.mydomain.EclipseCon.process. CheckInventoryAction as the class and bean as the type as shown
  below. You can also search for the class by clicking on the <emphasis>Browse...</emphasis> button.</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<figure>
<title>Action Handler</title>
<mediaobject> 
        <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="images/business_application/business_application_11.png"/>
        </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<para>Explanation: Now, you must wonder where this 
com.mydomain.EclipseCon.process.CheckInventoryAction class come from It comes from the 
eclipsecon-rules-bpm project we imported. The Java class has a single method that is executed 
when the &quot;Check Inventory&quot; node is reached in the process. The method just fires the rule we 
previously defined in process-order.drl. After the rule is executed, it updates the 
&quot;inventoryStatus&quot; component. Here is the method:</para>
<programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public void execute(ExecutionContext ctx) throws Exception {

  //get a handle to the rules engine
  Component c = (Component) Contexts.getApplicationContext().get(
			"orderWorkingMemory.component");
              WorkingMemory wm = (WorkingMemory) ((ManagedWorkingMemory) c
				.newInstance()).getWorkingMemory();

  //get the ordersHome variable that was set in OrderProcessor.
  OrdersHome order = (OrdersHome) ctx.getVariable("ordersHome");

  //Assert Orders to working memory and fire rules
  wm.assertObject(order.getInstance());
  wm.fireAllRules();

		
  //persist the updated Orders object
  order.persist();

  //set inventory status so decision node knows what to do
  ctx.setVariable("inventoryStatus", order.getInstance().getStatus());
  System.out.println("CHECK INVENTORY - STATUS: "
				+ order.getInstance().getStatus());
}
]]></programlisting>
<para>The &quot;inventoryStatus&quot; component is then used in the &quot;Inventory Decision&quot; node to determine 
which node to go to next. To do that, open the process-order.jpdl.xml file in the text editor and
 change the node from this</para>
 <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<decision name="Inventory Decision">
         <transition name="ship" to="Ship Order"></transition>
         <transition name="refund" to="Refund Order"></transition>
      </decision>
]]></programlisting>
<para>to this:</para>
<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<decision name="Inventory Decision" expression="#{inventoryStatus}">
         <transition name="ship" to="Ship Order"></transition>
         <transition name="refund" to="Refund Order"></transition>
      </decision>
]]></programlisting>
<para>Now, let&apos;s repeat the exercise to assign handler Java classes to the &quot;Ship Order&quot; and &quot;Refund Order&quot; nodes. </para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Associate &quot;Ship Order&quot; node with the com.mydomain.EclipseCon.process.ShipOrderAction 
bean</listitem>
<listitem>Associate &quot;Refund Order&quot; node with the com.mydomain.EclipseCon.process.SendRefundAction bean</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>As we described earlier, in a real world system, those two nodes would invoke Java code
 that perform real shipping and refunding tasks. But here we just print out a message as a proof
  of concept. You can look into their Java classes if you have time.</para>
</section>
<section id="StartTheProcessFromAWebAction">
<?dbhtml filename="StartTheProcessFromAWebAction.html"?>
<title>Start the process from a web action</title>
<para>Finally, we need  a &quot;hook&quot; to start the entire business process. We will add a new Process
 Order button to the Orders.xhtml file.</para>
 <para>You can add the new button right next to the existing &quot;Add orderdetails&quot; button. 
 Copy/paste the following button code in the actionButtons region:</para>
 <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<s:button id="buttonId" value="Process Order"
		  action="#{orderProcessor.startProcess}"
		  view="/Orders.xhtml"/>
]]></programlisting>
<para>Explanation: When you click on the Process Order button, Seam invokes 
the #{orderProcessor.startProcess} method, which in turn, starts the business process. The Java 
code for the #{orderProcessor} component is in the com.mydomain.EclipseCon.process.OrderProcessor 
class. Like other Java source files in the process package, the OrderProcessor.java is already 
copied to the EclipseCon project when you run the build.xml script from the imported rules-bpm
 project. Here is the content of the OrderProcessor.java file. The startProcess() method, which 
 is invoked from the Process Order button, starts the process-order process we just created.</para>
<programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Name("orderProcessor")
public class OrderProcessor {
	
	//Set the Orders object as a jBPM context variable
	@In(create = true)
	@Out(scope = ScopeType.BUSINESS_PROCESS)
	OrdersHome ordersHome;

	//Execute the jBPM process
	@CreateProcess(definition = "process-order")
	public String startProcess() {
		return "success";
	}
}
]]></programlisting>
</section>
<section id="TryItOut">
<?dbhtml filename="TryItOut.html"?>
<title>Try it out</title>
<para>Now save the project and restart the server to make sure that it is properly re-deployed. 
Navigate to the OrdersList page and enter &quot;In Process&quot; to the status field to search for 
un-processed orders.</para>
<para>Select one order and edit the order and change  the &quot;status&quot; field to &quot;in stock&quot; and 
click &quot;Done&quot;. Please enter the case exactly as indicated here:</para>
<figure>
<title>Order Edit Page</title>
<mediaobject> 
        <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="images/business_application/business_application_12.png"/>
        </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<para>Click the &quot;Process Order&quot; button.</para>
<figure>
<title>Order Details</title>
<mediaobject> 
        <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="images/business_application/business_application_13.png"/>
        </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<para>The business process should lead to the ShipOrderAction bean, which will print out the
 &quot;SHIP ORDER&quot; message in the console view tab at the bottom of the IDE screen.</para>
 <figure>
<title>Console View</title>
<mediaobject> 
        <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="images/business_application/business_application_14.png"/>
        </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<para>Select one order and change  the &quot;status&quot; field to &quot;back order&quot; and click &quot;Done&quot;. Please 
enter the case exactly as indicated here:</para>
<figure>
<title>Changing Status Field</title>
<mediaobject> 
        <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="images/business_application/business_application_15.png"/>
        </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<para>Click the &quot;Process Order&quot; button.</para>
<figure>
<title>Invoking Process Order</title>
<mediaobject> 
        <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="images/business_application/business_application_16.png"/>
        </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<para>The business process should invoke the SendRefundAction bean, which will print out the 
&quot;SEND REFUND&quot; message in the console view tab at the bottom of the IDE screen.</para>
<figure>
<title>Console Panel</title>
<mediaobject> 
        <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="images/business_application/business_application_17.png"/>
        </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<para>This example shows a simple example of the powerful jBPM and JBoss Rules runtimes 
integrated in a Seam application. We have also see how easy it is build these kinds of 
applications using the JBoss Developer Studio.</para>
</section>
    </chapter>
