<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="mavenized_seam" xreflabel="mavenized_seam">
	<?dbhtml filename="create_mavenized_seam.html"?>
	<chapterinfo>
		<keywordset>
			<keyword>JBoss Tools</keyword>
			<keyword>Seam</keyword>
			<keyword>JBDS</keyword>
		</keywordset>
	</chapterinfo>
	
	<title>Maven Integration for Seam Projects</title>
	<para>Starting from 3.1 M2 version <property>JBoss Tools</property> includes new Jboss Maven Integration plug-in which for now allows
	to  create mavenized Seam projects and enable Seam tools support for imported Maven projects.</para>
	
	<para>The Jboss Maven Integration requires <ulink url="http://m2eclipse.sonatype.org/"
		>m2eclipse</ulink> to be installed.</para>
	
	<note>
		<title>Note:</title>
		<para>For M2 release of <property>Jboss Tools</property> it is important to use m2eclipse <ulink
			url="http://m2eclipse.sonatype.org/update/">stable updatesite</ulink> or the <ulink url="http://m2eclipse.sonatype.org/releases/0.9.9.200906081351">latest integration build</ulink> that M2 was
			developed against. If you want to use the latest development release of m2eclipse you need to use the <ulink url="http://download.jboss.org/jbosstools/updates/nightly/trunk/">nightly builds</ulink> of
			<property>JBoss Tools</property>.</para>
	</note>
	
	<section id="create_mavenized_project">
	<title>Creating Maven ready Seam project</title>

	<para>Maven Integration makes the Seam Wizard capable of creating
		Maven ready projects to let Maven get the libraries instead of using the Seam runtime.</para>
	
	<para>To create a mavenized Seam project you should perform the following steps:</para>
	
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>Navigate to <emphasis>
				<property>File &gt; New Seam Project</property>.</emphasis> Give the project a meaningful name, specify a target runtime and server
				and select the proper configuration for your Seam project:</para>
			
			<figure>
				<title>Starting the Mavenized Seam Project</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/create_mavenized_seam/createMavenizedSeamProject.png"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</listitem>
		
		<listitem>
			<para>Click the <emphasis>
				<property>Modify</property></emphasis> button to enable the <emphasis>
					<property>Jboss Maven Integration</property></emphasis> facet:</para>
			
			<figure>
				<title>Enabling the Jboss Maven Integration Facet</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/create_mavenized_seam/jbossMavenIntegrationFacet.png"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</listitem>
		
		<listitem>
			<para>On the <property>JBoss M2 capabilities</property> page you&apos;ll be prompted to add the following maven properties: 
				groupId, artifactId, version, packaging, name and description. Here it&apos;s possible to set a maven version of Seam 
				and also decide whether to remove WTP classpath containers (where the path starts with org.eclipse.jst).
			</para>
			
			<figure>
				<title>Adjusting JBoss M2 Capabilities</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/create_mavenized_seam/jbossM2capabilities.png"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</listitem>
		
		<listitem>
			<para>On the <property>Seam Facet</property> page configure the Seam Facet settings and click <emphasis>
				<property>Finish</property>:</emphasis></para>
			
			<figure>
				<title>Seam Facet Settings</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/create_mavenized_seam/seamFacetPage.png"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	
	<para>The organized Seam project contains five projects with the Maven nature, builder, Maven classpath and the <emphasis>
		<property>pom.xml</property></emphasis> files added: 
		projectname, projectname-ear, projectname-ejb, projectname-parent and projectname-test.</para>
	
	<figure>
		<title>Mavenized Seam Project</title>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/create_mavenized_seam/mavenizedProjectStructure.png"/>
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</figure>
	</section>
	
	<section id="import_maven_project">
		<title>Existing Maven Projects Import</title>
		
		<para>Maven Integration includes the Seam Maven configurator which is called when importing a project, changing 
			<emphasis>
				<property>pom.xml</property></emphasis> and/or calling <emphasis>
					<property>Maven &gt; Update Project Configuration</property>.</emphasis>	When importing a Maven Seam project,  the Seam Maven configurator 
			picks up the settings set up in <emphasis>
				<property>pom.xml</property></emphasis> and adds to the project the following:</para>
		
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Seam nature</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Seam facet and dependent facets to the EJB, EAR and WAR projects</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>JBoss Maven Integration facet if the Maven project contains a dependency with the 
			org.jboss.seam groupId and an artifactId starting with 'jboss-seam'</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>other required facets (Web Module, Java, JSF, etc.)</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		
		<para>If the Seam version from <emphasis>
			<property>pom.xml</property></emphasis> matches a version of a Seam runtime configured in the workspace, 
			Seam configurator will set that runtime, otherwise no Seam runtime will be set and you&apos;ll have to set it manually under 
			<link linkend="project_pref">Seam Settings in the project preferences</link>.</para>
		
		<para>Seam configurator recognizes the Seam artifacts in the following way: the view folder is a web content folder from the WAR project, 
			the source folder is the first Eclipse source folder. If there is a folder containing &quot;hot&quot; in the name, it will be chosen as the action source folder. 
			Package is the first package that has children or doesn&apos;t have any subpackage.
		</para>
		
		<para>Configuring the Seam when importing a Maven project as well as a Seam Runtime, Seam artifacts and some facets could be suspended
			in the JBoss Maven Integration preferences (<emphasis>
				<property>Window &gt; Preferences &gt; JBoss Tools &gt; JBoss Maven Integration</property></emphasis>).</para>
		
		<figure>
			<title>JBoss Maven Integration Preferences</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/create_mavenized_seam/configure_maven_integration.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Relevant Resources Links</title>
		
		<para>In the <ulink url="http://in.relation.to/Bloggers/UsingMavenWithJBossTools">Using Maven with JBoss Tools</ulink> 
			article written by Max Andersen you&apos;ll find references to the 
		screencasts on how to use the examples of mavenized Seam projects provided by <property>JBoss Tools</property>.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
