<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="intro" xreflabel="intro">
    <?dbhtml filename="intro.html"?>
    <chapterinfo>
        <keywordset>
            <keyword>JBoss Tools</keyword>
            <keyword>Seam</keyword>
            <keyword>JBDS</keyword>
        </keywordset>
    </chapterinfo>

    <title>Introduction</title>

    <section>

        <title>What is Seam?</title>
        <para>This introduction will help you to understand what is <property>Seam</property>.</para>
        <para><property>Seam</property> is a fully featured application framework on top of Java EE
            5. It is also one of the most popular enterprise Java framework today. Seam deeply
            integrates many other standard-based or open source frameworks (e.g., JSF, EJB3, JMS,
            Web Services, jBPM, JBoss Rules, Ajax4jsf, RichFaces, Facelets, Spring, iText, Quartz,
            TestNG, etc.), and provides a single programming model for developers to
            &quot;drive&quot; those underlying frameworks via simple annotated POJOs (Plain
            Old Java Objects). It makes life easier for developers to tackle complex enterprise
            applications with many component frameworks.</para>
    </section>

    <section> 
        <title>Installation into Eclipse</title>

        <para>Here, we are going to explain how to install Seam plugin into Eclipse.</para>

        <para>Seam is a one module of JBoss Tools project. Since Seam has a dependence on other JBoss Tools modules we recommend you to install
            a bundle of all <ulink url="http://labs.jboss.com/tools/download/index.html">JBoss Tools plug-ins</ulink>. Installation instruction you can find on JBoss Wiki in <ulink url="http://labs.jboss.com/wiki/InstallingJBossTools">InstallingJBossTools</ulink> section.</para>
        
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Other relevant resources on the topic</title>

        <para>The <ulink url="http://seamframework.org/">Seam Framework</ulink> - Next generation enterprise Java development.</para>
        <para>All JBoss Developer Studio/JBoss Tools release documentation you can find at<ulink url="http://docs.jboss.org/tools/">http://docs.jboss.org/tools</ulink> in the corresponding release directory.</para>
        <para>The latest documentation builds are available at <ulink url="http://download.jboss.org/jbosstools/nightly-docs/">http://download.jboss.org/jbosstools/nightly-docs</ulink>.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
