<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="seam_preferences" xreflabel="seam_preferences">
    <!-- mark as new -->
    <?dbhtml filename="seam_preferences.html"?>
    <chapterinfo>
        <keywordset>
            <keyword>JBoss Tools</keyword>
            <keyword>Seam</keyword>
            <keyword>Preferences</keyword>
        </keywordset>
    </chapterinfo>

    <title>Seam Preferences</title>

    <para>In this chapter you get to know how Seam preferences can be modified during the
        development process.</para>

    <section id="gen_pref">
        <title>General Preferences</title>

        <para>Seam preferences can be set using the Seam preference page. Click on
                    <emphasis><property>Window > Preferences > JBoss Tools > Web >
                Seam</property>.</emphasis></para>

        <para>On this page you can manage the Seam Runtime. Use the appropriate buttons to
                <property>Add</property> more runtimes or to <property>Remove</property> those that
            are not needed.</para>

        <figure>
            <title>Seam Preferences Page</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/seam_preferences/seam_preferences1.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Clicking on <property>Edit</property> button you get the form where you can change the
            path of Seam runtime home folder, modify name and version. Press
                <property>Finish</property> to apply the changes.</para>

        <figure>
            <title>Edit Seam Runtime</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/seam_preferences/seam_preferences1_2.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <tip>
            <title>Tip:</title>
            <para>If you try to delete the Seam Runtime that is already in use by some project in the current workspace, then a warning message will appear. To confirm the removal press <property>OK</property>
            </para>
            <para>Besides, when you right-click on your Seam project with deleted runtime in Project Explorer and select<property> Properties > Seam Settings</property> the error message "Runtime &lt;runtime_name&gt; does not exist" will appear. </para>
        </tip>
        <section id="validator_pref">

            <title>Validator Preferences</title>

            <para>Seam preference page includes a subsection <property>Validator</property>. See
                        <emphasis><property>Window > Preferences > JBoss Tools > Web > Seam >
                        Validator</property>.</emphasis></para>
            <para>On this page you can choose a severity level for the various Seam validator
                problems. For example, if you want to ignore the case when component name is
                duplicated expand the <property>Components</property> node and select
                    <property>Ignore</property> next to <property>Duplicate component
                    name</property>. After that you won&apos;t see the error.</para>


            <figure>
                <title>Seam Validator Preference Page</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/seam_preferences/seam_preferences1_3.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>Notice, that in the <emphasis>
                    <property>Expression language</property>
                </emphasis> section there is now a preference for setting severity of EL Syntax. You
                can select whether the Seam validator displays an error, a warning or just ignore
                the EL Syntax error.</para>
            <note><para>There are references made between each EL and variable name, so you can revalidate a particular EL if a context variable was changed. This  makes parsing of each resource with referenced ELs much faster.</para></note>
            
    
            <figure>
                <title>Severity Preference for EL Syntax</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/seam_preferences/el_syntax_error.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        	
        	<para>The <emphasis>
        		<property>Revalidate unresolved ELs automatically</property></emphasis> option is enabled by default. 
        		If necessary, you can uncheck it. It may increase a performance for big complex projects.</para>

        	<para>In the upper right corner of the Seam Validator preferences page there is a <emphasis><property>Configure Project
                    Specific Settings</property></emphasis> link. Clicking on it you get the form where you can
                choose a project for specific setting. Project specific configuration allows you to
                have different validator settings for each project. Check the <emphasis><property>Show only
                    projects with project specific settings</property></emphasis> if you want to see the
                projects that have been already set. Click on <property>Ok</property>.</para>

            <figure>
                <title>Project Specific Configuration</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/seam_preferences/seam_preferences1_4.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>You get the validator properties page for chosen project. Check the
                    <property>Enable project specific settings</property> to be able to change the
                settings.</para>

            <note>
                <title>Note:</title>
                <para>You can open the same page by right clicking on the needed project in Package
                    Explorer, then <emphasis><property>Properties > Seam
                        Validator</property>.</emphasis></para>
            </note>

            <figure>
                <title>Validator Properties Page for Chosen Project</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/seam_preferences/seam_preferences1_5.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>


        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="project_pref">
        <title>Project Preferences</title>

        <para>Once Seam project is created you can modify its settings. Right click on Seam project
            in Project Explorer and select <emphasis><property>Properties &gt; Seam
                Settings</property>.</emphasis></para>
        <para>This project properties page allows you to have a flexible project layout. It means
            that you are not restricted with a specific project structure. You can use the Seam
            wizards (New Action, Form, Entity, etc.) on Maven, command line seam-gen or your own
            project structure. </para>

        <figure>
            <title>Properties for Seam Project</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/seam_preferences/seam_preferences2.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <tip>
            <title>Tip:</title>
            <para>The wizard doesn&apos;t allow the renaming of the artifacts listed in the Seam
                Settings. It&apos;s possible to do in the <property>Package Explorer</property>.
                See <link linkend="renaming_projects_folders">Renaming the Projects and
                    Folders</link>.</para>
        </tip>

        <para>Also notice, you are not required to use the <property>New Seam Project
                wizard</property> to benefit from Seam artifact wizards. You can just enable Seam on
            your existing project by checking <property>Seam Support</property> and targeting to
            Seam Runtime, and then configure the folders as you want.</para>

        <figure>
            <title>Properties for Seam Project when Seam runtime is not selected</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/seam_preferences/seam_preferences2_2.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <tip>
            <title>Tip:</title>
            <para>On the figure above fields for configuring Seam artifacts are dimmed because Seam
                Runtime is not selected.</para>
        </tip>

        <para>In Seam Wizards (New Action, Form, Entity, Conversation, Generate Entities) you can
            get a quick access to project settings using the <property>Settings</property> link in
            the upper right corner of each wizard.</para>

        <figure>
            <title>Quick Setting Link In Seam Wizards</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/seam_preferences/seam_preferences2_1.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="add_custom_capabilities">
        <title>Adding Custom Capabilities</title>

        <para><property>JBoss Tools</property> provides a possibility to add custom capabilities to any Seam project,
            i.e. add a support of additional frameworks built on top of JSF, such as <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>ADF</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Facelets</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>JBoss Rich Faces (versions 3.1, 3.2, 3.3)</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>To enable it, you should call the context menu for a Seam project and select <emphasis><property>JBoss
            Tools &gt; Add Custom Capabilities</property>.</emphasis> Then check the needed modules and press
            <emphasis><property>Finish</property>.</emphasis></para>
        
        <figure>
            <title> Custom Capabilities be added to Seam Project</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/seam_preferences/addCustomCapabilities.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>The next page displays all the updates that have been made to the project.</para>
        
        <figure>
            <title>Adding Custom Capabilities to Seam Project</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/seam_preferences/addCustomCapabilities2.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        
    </section>

</chapter>
