<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="intoduction">
    <?dbhtml filename="introduction.html"?>

    <chapterinfo>
        <keywordset>
            <keyword>JBoss Developer Studio</keyword>
            <keyword>Eclipse</keyword>
            <keyword>Java</keyword>
            <keyword>JBoss</keyword>
        </keywordset>
    </chapterinfo>

    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>If you prefer to develop web applications using Struts technology JBoss Tools also meet
        your needs. The professional developer toolset provides all necessary editors and wizards
        for creating Struts resources that enhances the process of building high-quality web
        applications.</para>
    <note>
        <title>Note:</title>
        <para>Note that JBoss Tools support the Struts 1.1, 1.2.x versions.</para>
    </note>

    <para>In this guide you will learn how to take advantage of Struts support that <property>JBoss Tools</property>
        provide.</para>

    <section id="struts_key_features">
        <title>Key Features of Struts Tools</title>

        <para>For a start, we propose you to look through the table of main features of Struts
            Tools:</para>

        <table>

            <title>Key Functionality for Struts Tools</title>
            <tgroup cols="3">

                <colspec colnum="1" align="left" colwidth="2*"/>
                <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="4*"/>
                <colspec colnum="3" align="left" colwidth="2*"/>

                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Feature</entry>
                        <entry>Benefit</entry>
                        <entry>Chapter</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry><para>Struts Support</para></entry>
                        <entry><para>Step-by-step wizards for creating a new struts project with a number
                            of predefined templates, importing existing ones and adding struts
                            capabilities to non-struts web projects.</para></entry>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="projects">struts support</link>
                        </entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><para>Support for Struts Configuration File</para></entry>
                        <entry><para>Working on file using three modes: diagram, tree and source.
                            Synchronization between the modes and full control over the code. Easy
                            moving around the diagram using the Diagram Navigator. Working with
                            struts projects that have multiple modules. Possibility to use Struts
                            configuration file debugger allowing to set break points on struts
                            diagram and then launch the server in debug mode.</para></entry>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="struts_config_editor">graphical editor for struts</link>
                            <link linkend="config_file_debugger">configuration file debugger</link>
                        </entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><para>Support for Struts modules</para></entry>
                        <entry><para>A Struts module (struts-config.xml) is automatically created while
                            creating a new project. There is also possibility to add new ones or edit
                            already existing modules in your existing project or while importing Struts project.</para></entry>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="modules">modules</link>
                        </entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><para>Verification and Validation</para></entry>
                        <entry><para>All occurring errors will be immediately reported by verification
                            feature, no matter in what view you are working. Constant validation and
                            errors checking allows to catch many of the errors during development
                            process that significantly reduces development time.</para></entry>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="project_verification">verification and validation</link>
                        </entry>

                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>Other relevant resources on the topic</title>
        
        <para>All JBoss Developer Studio/JBoss Tools documentation you can find on<ulink url="http://docs.jboss.org/tools/">JBoss Tools project page </ulink>.</para>
        <para>The latest documentation builds are available on<ulink url="http://download.jboss.org/jbosstools/nightly-docs/">nightly docs page</ulink>.</para>
        
    </section>
    
</chapter>
