<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="intoduction">
    <?dbhtml filename="introduction.html"?>

    <chapterinfo>
        <keywordset>
            <keyword>JBoss Developer Studio</keyword>
            <keyword>Eclipse</keyword>
            <keyword>Java</keyword>
            <keyword>JBoss</keyword>
        </keywordset>
    </chapterinfo>

    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
    	JBoss Developer Studio provides a number of editors and wizards that allow Struts developers to quickly and efficiently build high quality web applications.
    </para>
    <note>
        <title>Note:</title>
        <para>Note that JBoss Tools support the Struts 1.1, 1.2.x versions.</para>
    </note>

    <para>In this guide you will learn how to take advantage of Struts support that is provided by <property>JBoss Developer Studio</property>.</para>

    <section id="struts_key_features">
        <title>Key Features of Struts Tools</title>

        <para>The table below lists the main features provided by Struts Tools:</para>

        <table>

            <title>Key Functionality for Struts Tools</title>
            <tgroup cols="3">

                <colspec colnum="1" align="left" colwidth="2*"/>
                <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="4*"/>
                <colspec colnum="3" align="left" colwidth="2*"/>

                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Feature</entry>
                        <entry>Benefit</entry>
                        <entry>Chapter</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry><para>Struts Support</para></entry>
                        <entry>
                        	<para>
                        		Step-by-step wizards for creating a new Struts project with a number of predefined templates, importing existing ones and adding struts capabilities to non-Struts web projects.
                        	</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <xref linkend="projects"/>
                        </entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><para>Support for Struts Configuration File</para></entry>
                        <entry>
                        	<para>
                        		Working on files using three modes: diagram, tree and source. Synchronization between the modes and full control over the code. Easily move around the diagram using the Diagram Navigator. Working with struts projects that have multiple modules. The option to use the Struts configuration file debugger, which allows break points to be set on a Struts diagram and then launch the server in debug mode.
                        	</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <xref linkend="struts_config_editor"/>
                            <xref linkend="config_file_debugger"/>
                        </entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><para>Support for Struts modules</para></entry>
                        <entry>
                        	<para>
                        		A Struts module (<filename>struts-config.xml</filename>) is automatically created when creating a new project. There is also the option to add new or edit already existing modules in your existing project or while importing Struts project.
                        	</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <xref linkend="modules"/>
                        </entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><para>Verification and Validation</para></entry>
                        <entry>
                        	<para>
                        		All errors will be immediately reported by verification feature, no matter which view you are working in. Constant validation and errors checking allows developers to catch many of the errors during development process, which significantly reduces development time.
                        	</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <xref linkend="project_verification"/>
                        </entry>

                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>Other relevant resources on the topic</title>
        
        <para>
        	All JBoss Developer Studio/JBoss Tools documentation you can find on <ulink url="http://docs.jboss.org/tools/">JBoss Tools project page </ulink>.
        </para>
        <para>The latest documentation builds are available on <ulink url="http://download.jboss.org/jbosstools/nightly-docs/">nightly docs page</ulink>.</para>
        
    </section>
    
</chapter>
