<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="projects">
    <?dbhtml filename="projects.html"?>

    <chapterinfo>
        <keywordset>
            <keyword>JBoss Developer Studio</keyword>
            <keyword>Eclipse</keyword>
            <keyword>Java</keyword>
            <keyword>JBoss</keyword>
        </keywordset>
    </chapterinfo>

    <title>Projects</title>

    <para>JBoss Tools provide the following functionality when working with Struts:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Create new <property>Struts projects</property></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Import (open) existing Struts projects. You can import any project
            structure</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Add <property>Struts capabilities</property> to any existing Eclipse
            project</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Import and add Struts capabilities to any existing project created outside
                Eclipse.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Now, we&apos;ll focus on all these points more fully.</para>

    <section id="CreatingANewStrutsProjec745t">

        <title>Creating a New Struts Project</title>


        <para>JBoss Tools provides a New Struts Project Wizard that radically simplifies the process
            for getting started with a new Struts project. You just need to follow these steps:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Select<emphasis>
                        <property>File > New > Project...</property>
                    </emphasis> from the menu bar. Then, select <emphasis>
                        <property>JBoss Tools Web > Struts > Struts Project</property>
                    </emphasis> in this dialog box. Click <emphasis>
                        <property>Next</property>: </emphasis></para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <figure>
            <title>Selecting Struts Wizard</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_2.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>On this form, provide the <property>Project Name</property>. You can also
                    select where to create the project or use the default path.</para>
                <para>Next to <property>Struts Environment</property> set which Struts version to
                    use.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <figure>
            <title>Creating Struts Project</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_3.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <tip>
            <title>Tip:</title>
            <para>Don&apos;t put spaces in project names since some OS could experience problems
                with their processing and searching these files.</para>
        </tip>

        <para>You can select the KickStart template, then the project created will include a simple
            Hello World type application that is ready to run.</para>

        <figure>
            <title>Choosing Struts Template </title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_3_1.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Next, you register this application with the current servlet container defined
                    for your workspace (JBoss AS, by default) in order to allow you to test your
                    application more easily while still developing it. A new entry will be added in
                    the servlet container configuration file to enable running the application
                    in-place (called null deployment or link deployment). Uncheck the <emphasis
                        role="italic">
                        <property>&quot;Target Server&quot;</property>
                    </emphasis> check box if for some reason you don&apos;t want to register
                    your application at this point.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <figure>
            <title>Registering The Project at Server</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_4.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>On the next form, you can select the TLD files to include in this
                project:</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <figure>
            <title>Selecting Tag Libraries</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_5.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>After the project is created, you should have the following project structure (if you
            used the KickStart template):</para>

        <figure>
            <title>Project Structure</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_6.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <tip>
            <title>Tip:</title>
            <para>If you want to hide the jar files from Web App Libraries in view, select the
                down-pointing arrow in the upper right corner, select
                <emphasis>Filters...</emphasis>, check the box next to Name filter patterns
                (matching names will be hidden), and type *.jar into the field. Then, click OK.
            </para>
        </tip>
    </section>
    <section id="ImportingAnExistingStrutsProjectWithAnyStructure9653">

        <title>Importing an Existing Struts Project with Any Structure</title>

        <para>For detailed information on migration projects to JBoss Developer Studio see the Migration Guide.</para>

    </section>
    <section id="AddingStrutsCapabilityToAnExistingWebApplication532">

        <title>Adding Struts Capability to an Existing Web Application</title>

        <para>Here, we&apos;ll consider how to add Struts functionality (Struts libraries, tag
            libraries and a Struts configuration file) to any existing Web application project in
            your Eclipse workspace.</para>

        <para>By adding a Struts Nature to your project, you can now edit files using JBoss Tools
            editors, such as the <link linkend="struts_config_editor">Struts configuration
            editor</link> and the JBoss Tools JSP editor. To take advantage of this just right-click
            the project and select <emphasis>
                <property>JBoss Tools > Add Struts Capabilities</property>
            </emphasis> from the context menu. This will start the process of adding all necessary
            libraries and files to make a Web Struts project from your one.</para>

        <figure>
            <title>Adding Struts Capabilities</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_7.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>In the wizard you should point to location of your deployment descriptor file web.xml
            and name of the project.</para>

        <figure>
            <title>Choosing Project Location</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_8.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>After hitting <emphasis>
                <property>Next</property>, </emphasis> you will see the following screen. This
            screen simply means that you need to add at least one Struts module to your project to
            make this project a Struts project. Adding a Struts module means that a new
            struts-config.xml will be added to your project and registered in the web.xml file. In
            addition, all required Struts libraries will be added. To add a Struts module, select
            the <emphasis>
                <property>Add Struts Support</property>
            </emphasis> button.</para>
        <figure>
            <title>Project Modules</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_9.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Here you can select what Struts <property>Version</property>, <property>Servlet
            Class</property>, <property>URL Pattern</property> and <property>TLD</property>s to add
            to this project.</para>

        <figure>
            <title>Selecting Struts Support Options</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_10.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>When done, you will see the default Struts module configuration information. See how
            to Edit <link linkend="modules">Struts modules</link>.</para>

        <figure>
            <title>Project Configuration Information</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_11.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>On the last screen you can set the different folders for your project as well as
            register this application with a servlet container. If you want the libraries (.jar
            files) will be automatically added to your project, click on the checkbox <emphasis>
                <property>Add Libraries</property>.</emphasis></para>

        <figure>
            <title>Registering the Project at Server</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_12.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>When done, you can open and edit the struts-config.xml file using useful Struts
            configuration file editor provided by JBDS. (The Struts configuration is shown below in
            the Tree viewer).</para>

        <figure>
            <title>Struts-config.xml File</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_13.png" scale="75"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Relevant Resources Links</title>
        
        <para>You can find more in-depth explanation on how to work with special wizards, editors and views that can
            be used in various scenarios while developing Struts applications in our Visual Web Tools Guide.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
