<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="editors">
    <?dbhtml filename="editors.html"?>
    <chapterinfo>
        <keywordset>
            <keyword>JBoss Developer Studio</keyword>
            <keyword>Eclipse</keyword>
            <keyword>Struts Tools</keyword>
            <keyword>Java</keyword>
            <keyword>JBoss</keyword>
        </keywordset>
    </chapterinfo>

    <title>Editors</title>
    <para>In this chapter we&apos;ll introduce you to featured graphical editors for specific
    Struts files such as Struts Configuration files, Tiles files, Struts Validation files and web.xml.</para>
	
	<section id="webxml_editor">
		<title>Web.xml Editor</title>
		
		<para>The <emphasis>
			<property>web.xml</property></emphasis> file inside the <emphasis>
				<property>WEB-INF</property></emphasis> folder is a deployment descriptor file for a Web Application. It 
			describes the servlets and other components and deployment properties that make up your application.</para>
		
		<para><property>JBoss Tools</property> add the <emphasis>
			<property>web.xml</property></emphasis> file to created Struts project automatically and provides a special editor for its editing.
			See the Visual Web Tools guide that gives a descriptive information on the <ulink url="&jsflink;#GraphicalWebApplicationFileEditor">web.xml editor</ulink>.</para>
	</section>
	
    <section id="struts_config_editor">

        <title>Graphical Editor for Struts Configuration Files</title>
        <para>First, let&apos;s dwell on the Struts Configuration file editor.</para>
        <para>This editor  has three views with different representation of <emphasis>
                <property>struts-config.xml</property>: </emphasis>Diagram, Tree and Source. The
            views can be selected via the tabs at the bottom of the editor. Any changes made in one
            view are immediately visible when you switch to any other view.</para>

        <para>Now, we&apos;ll consider every view in more detail.</para>
        <section id="StrutsDiagramMode453">

            <title>Diagram View</title>

            <para>The Diagram view graphically displays the Web flow of the application defined in
                the Struts configuration file.</para>

            <figure>
                <title>Diagram View</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_14.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>The Diagram view allows to edit navigation in your Struts application. Just by
                right-clicking anywhere on the diagram, you can use a context menu to create the
                building blocks of a Struts application:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Actions</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Global forwards</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Global exceptions</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>JSP Pages</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <figure>
                <title>Diagram Context Menu</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_15.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>Along the upper-left side of the editor is a stack of seven icons for changing the
                behavior of the cursor in the diagram. </para>

            <figure>
                <title>Editor Icons</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_16.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>The first icon switches to the default regular selection cursor, the second to the
                marquee selection cursor and the third to the new connection cursor. The last four
                icons switch the cursor to an insert cursor for each type of Struts build block
                listed above (and in the order listed).</para>

            <para>For instance, clicking on the first of these four icons (the one with the gears)
                will switch the cursor to insert actions. Clicking anywhere in the diagram with this
                cursor has the same effect as right-click and selecting <emphasis>
                    <property>Add > Action...</property>
                </emphasis> from the context menu with the regular cursor active. It&apos;s just
                more efficient to use this cursor if you&apos;re adding more than one action at
                once.</para>


        </section>
        <section id="StrutsTreeMode42">

            <title>Tree View</title>

        	<para>The Tree view represents the different elements of the Struts application that are organized into functional categories 
        		on the left-hand side and a form for editing the properties of currently selected items on the right-hand side.</para>

            <figure>
                <title>Tree View</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_17.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>        	
        
            <para>You can right-click on any node in the category tree and perform appropriate
                operations through a context menu. For instance, by right-clicking on the
                action-mappings category node, you can add new actions to the application.</para>

            <figure>
                <title>Tree Context Menu</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_18.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        	
        	<para>Let&apos;s consider the tree on the left more closely.</para>
        	
        	<itemizedlist>
        		<listitem><para>Under the <emphasis>
        			<property>data-sources</property></emphasis> node you can create a Data Source object that will be configured 
        			and made available as a servlet context attribute.</para></listitem>
        		
        		<listitem><para>The <emphasis>
        			<property>form-beans</property></emphasis> node is meant for creating a set of form bean descriptors for this module. 
        			Every created element under this node is a JavaBean that implements the org.apache.struts.action.ActionForm class. 
        			Use the Properties editor on the right to adjust properties specific to every created form-bean.</para></listitem>
        		
        		<listitem><para>The <emphasis>
        			<property>global-exceptions</property></emphasis> node is intended for registering the handlers for the exceptions 
        			that might be thrown by an Action object.</para></listitem>
        		
        		<listitem><para>Use the <emphasis>
        			<property>global-forwards</property></emphasis> node to add, edit or delete a global forwards that represent
        			ActionForward objects available to all Action objects as a return value.</para></listitem>
        		
        		<listitem><para>The <emphasis>
        			<property>controller</property></emphasis> node allows you to configure the controller properties.</para></listitem>
        		
        		<listitem><para>Under the <emphasis>
        			<property>resources</property></emphasis> node you can add, delete, or edit message resources.</para></listitem>
        		
        		<listitem><para>Under the <emphasis>
        			<property>plug-ins</property></emphasis> node you can define a Struts plug-in. Right-click the node, select <emphasis>
        				<property>Create Plug-in</property></emphasis> 
        			and specify the plug-ib <emphasis>
        				<property>Id</property></emphasis> and <emphasis>
        					<property>ClassName</property></emphasis> by pointing to the Java class which implements the org.apache.struts.action.PlugIn interface. </para></listitem>
        		
        	</itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section id="StrutsSourceMode9655">

            <title>Source View</title>

            <para>In the Source view, you have complete editing control of the underlying XML
                coding.</para>

            <figure>
                <title>Source View</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_19.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            
            <para>When working in Source view, you always have all the following features available:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Content Assist</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Open On Selection</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>File Folding</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>You can take advantage of <ulink url="&jsflink;#CodeAssistAndDynamicCodeAssist42BasedOnProjectData">code assist</ulink>.</para>
            <figure>
                <title>Code Assist</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_20.png" scale="85"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>The editor will also immediately flag any errors.</para>

            <figure>
                <title>Errors in Source View</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_21.png" scale="85"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>Finally, you can use the Outline view with the editor to easily navigate through
                the file.</para>

            <figure>
                <title>Outline View</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_22.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            
            <para>Find more information about editor features <ulink url="&jsflink;#editors_features"
                >here</ulink>.</para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="GraphicalEditorForTilesFiles132">

        <title>Graphical Editor for Tiles Files</title>
        <para>Here, you&apos;ll know how to make use of the special graphical editor for Tiles configuration files.</para>
        <para>The editor has three main views: Tree, Diagram and Source.
            The views can be selected via the tabs at the bottom of the editor. Any changes made in
            one view are immediately visible when you switch to any other view.</para>

       <para>Before we consider each view of the editor, let&apos;s look at the way of creating new Tiles files.</para>
        <section id="CreateNewTilesFile1422">

            <title>Create New Tiles File</title>

            <para>To create new Tiles files, right click any folder and select <emphasis>
                    <property>New &gt; Tiles File</property>. </emphasis></para>
            <figure>
                <title>Creating a New Tiles File</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_23.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </section>
        <section id="StrutsTreeView896">

            <title>Tree View</title>

            <para>The Tree view represents the different elements of the Tiles file that are
                organized into functional categories on the left-hand side and a form for editing
                the properties of currently selected items on the right-hand side.</para>
            <figure>
                <title>Tree View</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_24.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>To edit the file, simply right click any node and select among the available
                actions.</para>
            <figure>
                <title>Editing in Tiles Editor</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_25.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </section>
        <section id="StrutsDiagramView4643">

            <title>Diagram View</title>

            <para>The Diagram view allows you to create complex Tiles files in the form of a
                diagram.</para>
            <figure>
                <title>Diagram Mode</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_26.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>To create new definitions, simply right click anywhere in the diagram.</para>
            <figure>
                <title>Creating New Definition</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_27.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>You can also use the Diagram toolbar to make editing easier.</para>
            <figure>
                <title>Diagram Toolbar</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_28.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para> It contains four icons for changing the cursor state. The first one is the
                default cursor state for selecting existing nodes. The second icon is marquee
                selector. The third is used for creating new connections and the last one is for
                adding definition template to the content.</para>
        </section>
        <section id="StrutsSource75">

            <title>Source</title>

            <para>The other view of the <property>Tiles editor</property> is the Source view that
                gives you full control over the source. Any changes here will immediately appear in
                other modes when you switch to them.</para>
            
            <para>When working in Source view, you always have all following features available:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Content Assist</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Open On Selection</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            
            <figure>
                <title>Source View</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_29.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para><ulink url="&jsflink;#CodeAssistAndDynamicCodeAssist42BasedOnProjectData">Code
                assist</ulink> is available in the Source mode.</para>
            <figure>
                <title>Code Assist</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_30.png" scale="85"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>Any errors are immediately reported as shown below:</para>
            <figure>
                <title>Errors Reporting</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_31.png" scale="75"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>You can also use the Outline view together with the editor&apos;s Source mode.
                It provides an easier navigation through the file.</para>
            <figure>
                <title>Outline View</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_32.png" scale="85"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="GraphicalEditorForStrutsValidationFiles86">

        <title>Graphical Editor for Struts Validation Files</title>

        <para>Providing full support for development Struts applications JBoss Tools comes with a
            visual validation editor. To open the editor double-click on the validation file or if you don&apos;t have it create a new one.</para>
            
            <para>To create a new validation file, right click any folder in
            Project Explorer and select <emphasis>
                <property>File > New > Other...</property>
            </emphasis>from the context menu and then <emphasis>
                <property>JBoss Tools Web > Struts > Validation File</property>. </emphasis></para>
        <figure>
            <title>Creating New Validation File</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_33.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>The validation editor works with five modes: Formsets, Validators, Constants and
            standard Tree and Source that you can easily switch over using tabs at the bottom of the
            editor.</para>
        <para>The Formsets view shows forms and their elements on the left side and the dialogue for
            defining their validation rules on the right side.</para>
        <figure>
            <title>Formsets View</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_34.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>The Constants view let you set constant values for your validation rules.</para>
        <figure>
            <title>Constansts View</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_35.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>The validation file can also be viewed in a Tree view.</para>
        <figure>
            <title>Tree View</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_36.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>At any point you have full control over the source by switching to the Source view.
            Any editing in this view will immediately be available in other views of the editor.</para>
        <figure>
            <title>Source View</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_37.png" scale="85"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>You can also open your own custom or Struts-standard <emphasis>
                <property>validation-rules.xml</property>
            </emphasis> file.</para>
        <para>The Validators view shows the validation rules for a selected validator. You can of
            course add your own rules.</para>
        <figure>
            <title>Validators View</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_38.png" scale="75"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>Here are the validation rules shown in the Source mode.</para>
        <figure>
            <title>Validation Rules</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/struts/struts_39.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </section>
</chapter>
