<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="DatabaseTools" xreflabel="DatabaseTools">
  <?dbhtml filename="DatabaseTools.html"?>
<title>Database Tools</title>

<section id="DatabaseExplorer">
<?dbhtml filename="DatabaseExplorer.html"?>
<title>Database Explorer</title>
<para>Database Explorer</para>

<para>The Data Tools plug-in provides two special views: the Database Explorer view and the DB Output view. The Database Explorer view is where you will create connections, view your database objects, and launch actions from those objects. The DB Output view is where query results and messages are displayed.</para>

<para>You can open either one by selecting <emphasis>Window/Show View/Other...</emphasis> from the menu bar and then choosing the appropriate view under the Data node.</para>

<para>DatabaseExplorerShowViewDatabaseExplorerShowView</para>

<para>The Database Explorer view shows all available connections. To create a new connection right-click anywhere in the window and select <emphasis>New Connection...</emphasis> from the context menu.</para>
<para>Then, follow these steps:</para>

<para>   1.</para>

<para>      Specify a name for this connection.</para>

<para>      DatabaseExplorerNewConnectionStep1DatabaseExplorerNewConnectionStep1</para>
<para>   2.</para>

<para>      Select a Database Manager from the tree on the left and specify connection parameters on the right. You can test the connection by selecting the Test Connection button.</para>

<para>      DatabaseExplorerNewConnectionStep2DatabaseExplorerNewConnectionStep2</para>
<para>   3.</para>

<para>      On this page you can filter the database objects that are retrieved. If you are connecting to a database with a large number of database objects, it is important to filter appropriately to reduce the number of tables returned.</para>

<para>      DatabaseExplorerNewConnectionStep3DatabaseExplorerNewConnectionStep3</para>
<para>   4.</para>

<para>      The summary page gives you a chance to review the parameters for this connection.</para>

<para>      DatabaseExplorerNewConnectionStepLastDatabaseExplorerNewConnectionStepLast</para>

<para>In the Database Explorer, you will see a tree structure representing your connection and the database objects retrieved.</para>

<para>DatabaseExplorerConnectionTreeDatabaseExplorerConnectionTree</para>

<para>To sample the data from a table, select the table in the Database Explorer and select Sample Contents from the context menu.</para>

<para>DatabaseExplorerSampleDataDatabaseExplorerSampleData</para>

<para>This displays the table's sample data in the DB Output view.</para>

<para>DatabaseExplorerSampleDataResult</para>

</section>

<section id="SQLScrapbook">
<?dbhtml filename="SQLScrapbook.html"?>
<title>SQL Scrapbook</title>
<para>SQL Scrapbook</para>

<para>ORM Studio comes with a database query tool called SQL Scrapbook. You can write any SQL statements against the database for which you have created a connection.</para>

<para>To open the SQL Scrapbook, right-click a connection and select Open SQL Scrapbook from the context menu.</para>

<para>SQLScrapBook</para>

<para>You will be prompted for a file name for saving the contents of the Scrapbook. Then the SQL Scrapbook editor will appear above the Database Explorer view. You can type in a SQL statement like this:</para>

<para>SQLScrapStatement</para>

<para>To execute the statement, select the Execute the SQL Statement icon in the toolbar.</para>

<para>SQLScrapExecuteIcon</para>

<para>The result is shown in the DB Output view that appears below the SQL Scrapbook.</para>

<para>SQLScrapResult</para>
</section>

<section id="QuantumDB plug-in  ">
<?dbhtml filename="QuantumDB plug-in  .html"?>
<title>QuantumDB plug-in  </title>
<para>QuantumDB Plug-In</para>

<para>We recommend to use QuantumDB free plug-in for database access. It works very well with RHDS. Please visit QuantumDB home page.</para>

<para>QuantumDB supports the following databases:</para>

<para>    * Adabas</para>
<para>    * DB2</para>
<para>    * DB2 on AS400</para>
<para>    * HSQLDB</para>
<para>    * Informix</para>
<para>    * MySQL</para>
<para>    * Oracle</para>
<para>    * Pointbase</para>
<para>    * PostgreSQL</para>
<para>    * Sybase</para>

</section>

</chapter>