<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="introduction">
    <?dbhtml filename="introduction.html"?>

    <chapterinfo>
        <keywordset>
            <keyword>JBoss Developer Studio</keyword>
            <keyword>Eclipse</keyword>
            <keyword>Java</keyword>
            <keyword>JBoss</keyword>
            <keyword>JSF Tools</keyword>
        </keywordset>
    </chapterinfo>

    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
    	JSF Tools are especially designed to support JSF and JSF-related technologies. JSF Tools provide extensible tools for building JSF-based applications as well as adding JSF capabilities to existing web projects, importing JSF projects and choosing any JSF implementation while developing JSF application.
    </para>

    <para>
    	This guide provides the information on JSF tooling you need to allow you to quickly develop JSF applications with far fewer errors.
    </para>

    <section id="jsf_key_features">
        <title>Key Features of JSF Tools</title>

        <para>The table below lists the functionality provided by the JSF Tools.</para>

        <table>
            <title>Key Functionality for JSF Tools</title>
            <tgroup cols="3">

                <colspec colnum="1" align="left"  colwidth="2*"/>
                <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="4*"/>
                <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="2*"/>

                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Feature</entry>
                        <entry>Benefit</entry>
                        <entry>Chapter</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    
                    <row>
                        <entry>JSF and Facelets support</entry>
                        <entry>
                        	Step-by-step wizards for creating new JSF and Facelets projects with a number of predefined templates, importing existing ones and adding JSF capabilities to non-JSF web projects.
                        </entry>
                        <entry><xref linkend="jsf_support"/></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Flexible and customizable project template management</entry>
                        <entry>Jump-start development with the supplied templates or easily create customized templates for re-use.</entry>
                        <entry>
                            <xref linkend="projects"/>
                        </entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Support for JSF Configuration File</entry>
                        <entry>
                        	Work on a file using three modes: diagram, tree and source. Automatic synchronization between the modes and full control over the code. Easily move around the diagram using the Diagram Navigator.
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <xref linkend="jsf_config_file"/>
                        </entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Support for Managed Beans</entry>
                        <entry>Adding new managed beans, generating code for attributes, properties and getter/setter methods.</entry>
                        <entry>
                            <xref linkend="managed_beans"/>
                        </entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Support for Custom Converters and Validators</entry>
                        <entry>Fast creation of custom converters and validators with a tree view of the <filename>faces-config.xml</filename> file.</entry>
                        <entry>
                            <xref linkend="creation_and_registration"/>
                        </entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Verification and Validation</entry>
                        <entry>
                        	All errors will be immediately reported by verification feature, no matter in what view you are working. Constant validation and error checking allows you to catch many of the errors during development process that significantly reduces development time.
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <xref linkend="jsf_project_verification"/>
                        </entry>

                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Other relevant resources on the topic</title>
        <para>All JBoss Developer Studio and JBoss Tools release documentation can be found on the <ulink url="http://docs.redhat.com/docs/en-US/JBoss_Developer_Studio/index.html">RedHat Documentation</ulink> website. </para>
        <para>Nightly documentation builds are available at <ulink url="http://download.jboss.org/jbosstools/nightly-docs/">http://download.jboss.org/jbosstools/nightly-docs</ulink>.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
