<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="introduction" xreflabel="introduction">
  <?dbhtml filename="introduction.html"?>
  <chapterinfo>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>JBoss Tools</keyword>
      <keyword>Eclipse</keyword>
      <keyword>Java</keyword>
      <keyword>JBoss</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </chapterinfo>
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>The following chapters describe how to deal with classic/old style of Struts development. We
    recommend users to use JBoss Seam to
    simplify development, but until then you can read about classical Struts usage here.</para>

  <para>We are going to show you how to create a simple <emphasis>
      <property>Struts application</property>
    </emphasis> using the JBoss Tools. The completed application will ask a user to enter
    a name and click a button. The resulting new page will display the familiar message,
    &quot;Hello &lt;name&gt;!&quot;</para>
  <para>This document will show you how to create such an application from the beginning, along the
    way demonstrating some of the powerful features of JBoss Tools. With the help of our tutorial you will design the
    application, generate stub code for the application, fill in the stub coding, compile the
    application, and finally run it all from inside the Eclipse.</para>
  
  <section>
    <title>Key Features Struts Tools</title>
  
    <para>For a start, we propose you to look through the table of main features of Struts
      Tools:</para>
    <table>
      
      <title>Key Functionality of Struts Tools</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        
        <colspec colnum="1" align="left" colwidth="2*"/>
        <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="4*"/>
        
        
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Feature</entry>
            <entry>Benefit</entry>
           
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Struts Support</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Step-by-step wizards for creating a new struts project with a number
              of predefined templates, importing existing ones and adding struts
              capabilities to non-struts web projects.</para></entry>
            
          </row>
          
          <row>
            <entry><para>Support for Struts Configuration File</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Working on file using three modes: diagram, tree and source.
              Synchronization between the modes and full control over the code. Easy
              moving around the diagram using the Diagram Navigator. Working with
              struts projects that have multiple modules. Possibility to use Struts
              configuration file debugger allowing to set break points on struts
              diagram and then launch the server in debug mode.</para></entry>
            
          </row>
          
          <row>
            <entry><para>Support for Struts modules</para></entry>
            <entry><para>A Struts module (struts-config.xml) is automatically created while
              creating a new project. There is also possibility to add new ones or edit
              already existing modules in your existing project or while importing Struts project.</para></entry>
            
          </row>
          
          <row>
            <entry><para>Verification and Validation</para></entry>
            <entry><para>All occurring errors will be immediately reported by verification
              feature, no matter in what view you are working. Constant validation and
              errors checking allows to catch many of the errors during development
              process that significantly reduces development time.</para></entry>
            
            
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>
  
  
  
  <section>
    <title>Other relevant resources on the topic</title>
    
    <para>All JBoss Developer Studio/JBoss Tools release documentation you can find at<ulink url="http://docs.jboss.org/tools/">http://docs.jboss.org/tools</ulink> in the corresponding release directory.</para>
    <para>The latest documentation builds are available at <ulink url="http://download.jboss.org/jbosstools/nightly-docs/">http://download.jboss.org/jbosstools/nightly-docs</ulink>.</para>
    
  </section>
  
</chapter>
